A Guide to the Vale Club Records, 1934-2016 (bulk 1984-2016)
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Vale Club Records, 1934-2016 (bulk 1984-2016)
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-53
3.75 linear feet
The Vale Club Records consist of 3.75 linear feet, and spans the years 1934-2016, with the bulk of the collection ranging from 1984-2016. Contents consist of scrapbooks, correspondence, newsletters, maps, handbooks, cookbooks, check request forms, and postcards.
Vale Club
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Gift of Vale Club members Trish Strat and Mary Colombi in Summer 2013.
Historical and Biographical Information
In 1934, Florence Jodzies founded the Vale Home Demonstration Club. She, along with a group of resourceful women, laid the groundwork for a women’s club that would become a local landmark. Although the Vale Club was only one of many Home Demonstration clubs, it is unique in large part because of the efforts made by Florence Jodzies.
Originally from Ohio, Florence Jodzies was first appointed Senior Stenographer at the Extension Service of the University of Maryland, College Park in 1921. She later moved to Vale (Fairfax County, Virginia) with her second husband in 1934 and founded the Vale Home Demonstration Club. While Jodzies never served as president of the club she was nevertheless an active member of the community. During her life she served as an officer in the Virginia Federation of Home Demonstration Clubs, vice president of the Fairfax County Council of Home Demonstration Clubs, and even the chairman of the state library. She was a strong advocate for rural communities’ access to libraries.
The building which now houses the Vale Club was originally a one-room schoolhouse built in 1884. During the Great Depression the Vale School was closed due to the consolidation of schools. Although Vale School’s closure resulted in losing a central community place, it allowed for the Vale Home Demonstration Club to petition for its use as a community center. As a result, the Home Demonstration was granted exclusive use of the Vale property in 1935, a mere year after the club’s inception. By 1938 they raised enough money to purchase the schoolhouse for two-hundred and seventy dollars.
Before the Home Demonstration Club acquired the schoolhouse, a second room had been added onto the building in 1912. Since the acquisition in 1935, the schoolhouse’s upkeep has been an integral part of the club’s activities. Notable projects completed by the Vale Club include the installation of electricity in 1940, a well-structure built in 1951, a new roof in 1985, indoor plumbing installed in 1990 (and the 1884 privy torn down), and in 2005 the construction of a storage shed. In 1950, the club replaced the first room’s maple hardwood floor, and in 1995 replaced linoleum floors with hardwood floors in the second room. Both rooms in the schoolhouse still retain their original beadboard paneled ceiling and wood cornices and also feature reproduction light fixtures and ceiling fans.
During the years between the advent of the club and purchasing the school, the club solidified itself in the local community by hosting its first Vale Club Community Exhibit in 1936, and in 1937 sponsored the community’s first 4-H Club. Soon after, the ladies of the club established themselves even further with their World War II relief efforts by sewing for the Red Cross, salvaging various materials (fats, metals, paper, and so on), planting victory gardens, and becoming home certified nurses.
Since 1934, Vale Club had also been associated with the Extension Club. The purpose of the Extension Club, which began nationally in 1913, was to educate and organize farm women so they could learn life skills such as sewing, cooking, sanitation, and even beautification. Vale Club endeavored to foster a place in which rural women could learn valuable skills including canning, dressmaking, furniture refinishing, and basic health care.
The Vale Club remained associated with the Extension Club until 1999. In early 1998, deliberations to end the affiliation began. These discussions are evidenced by council meeting minutes, as well as letters written in the Extension Line newsletter. By August 1998, the Extension Line newsletter urged members to attend the next meeting to vote on the fate of the relationship. Evidently, the members were in favor of not continuing with the Extension Club. After the vote had been cast, the end of the association escalated quickly. November’s council meeting brought proposed distribution of funds, and in January 1999 the decision to dissolve the club was finalized.
Despite the various changes imposed upon the Vale Club, efforts to tie members together never ceased. In 1980, the Gourmet Club began its first meal gatherings, a series of meetings that occurred throughout the year and endures today. Although there is usually an overarching yearly theme, each dinner party has its own unique twist. For example, the 1995-1996 year theme “Affairs to Remember” features classic Hollywood films. Appropriately, each dinner theme corresponds with a different movie, such as the club’s pairing of the film Like Water for Chocolate with Mexican cuisine. These yearly themed dinners are recorded in annually published cookbooks which include menus, recipes, and the names and contact information for the hostesses and Gourmet Club members. Other efforts to bring club members together include dinner dance/auctions for Valentine's Day, Mardis Gras, and even excursions into Washington, D.C.
By the mid-2000s, the club began sending care packages to soldiers. These care packages are created and sent bi-yearly and include various items such as snacks, puzzles, and toiletries. The club has also been active in helping with the Sunrise Teen Alcohol and Drug Treatment Center.
Although the club has changed since its inception in the 1930s, it has retained its fundamental traditions. These include: monthly meetings, an annual fall fair, use of the schoolhouse for community meetings, assisting community members in need, and raising money for the upkeep of the schoolhouse. While the face of Vale Club has changed, membership has fluctuated, and activities have evolved, it has sustained itself as a pillar of the local community and is still active to date.
Scope and Content
Series 1: Administrative Files
Sub-series 1-1: Extension Club, 1998-1999, Box 1
This sub-series contains information regarding the end of Vale’s relationship with the Extension club. It includes documents and reports dealing directly with the dissolution of the club as well as peripheral records. The chief documents detailing the end of the relationship with the Extension club can be found in the Council Meeting reports. Records not directly concerning the dissolution are the newsletters: Old Dominion Echoes and The Extension Line. Additionally, there are reports detailing the accomplishments of the Extension club, reports by the club president, and a Gift of Knowledge Grant information page and application.
Sub-series 1-2: Geographic Boundaries, 2003, Box 1
The Friends of Vale Schoolhouse drafted the documents in this sub-series which deal with the legalities and bylaws concerning the geographic boundaries of the club, especially in regards to membership eligibility. The problem is traced to an influx of new members around 1985-86, accepting members living outside the geographic borders of the club. Also included are a FVS Boundary Committee meeting outline agenda, a draft of the problem, possible solutions, a history of the boundaries, and two maps highlighting the club’s boundary. Additionally, there is a copy of a memorandum from the club’s attorney concerning the boundaries.
Sub-series 1-3: Vale Associates Packet, 1999, Box 1
Includes official documentation regarding the club’s by-laws (revised 1987), a copy of the deed to the schoolhouse, certificate of incorporation, and a chronological history of Vale Club. Other documents include Virginia Code section 58.1-3609 and a copy of the article of amendment. Although a table of contents is included, not every record is accounted for. Missing records include “A Brief History of Vale Associates,” 501c(3) History by Anne Smith, and Virginia Senate Bill No. 23 (3-6-64).
Sub-series 1-4: Receipts and Finances, 1992-1999, Box 1
This sub-series is comprised of receipts, invoices, check-request forms, and rental agreements. Charges are primarily in regards to plumbing, landscape, maintenance, etc. Also included is a check request, letter regarding the completing of work, and a rental receipt in regards to the Boy Scout Project in Series 2-1.
Series 2: Social and Activities
Sub-series 2-1: Boy Scout Proposal, 1997, Box 1
This sub-series contains the proposal by Eagle Scout Barry McCabe for building and continuing an existing fence and landscape maintenance. It describes in detail the beneficiaries of the project as well relating the present condition of the Vale Schoolhouse. A list of supplies, tools, and estimated costs are included. Additionally, there is a comprehensive schedule to complete the project, work details, a financial plan, and safety considerations. Also, there is a map of the plan drafted and printed on a computer (printed on color-printer).
Sub-series 2-2: Vale Club Fair, 1984-1999, Box 1
Records in this sub-series are comprised of a variety of documents concerning the Vale Club Fair. These documents include newspaper clippings and a press release. There are also administrative records concerning fair vendors, food, activities, and notes from planning meetings. Additionally, various financial documents are included that cover Treasurer’s Reports, and money collection.
Sub-series 2-3: Fundraisers, Events, Awards, and Recognitions 1990-2012, Box 1
This sub-series includes invitations, drink menus, and auction booklets from Mardi Gras, Valentine's Day parties, and other auctions. Evidence of party planning is demonstrated through hand-written music lists for a DJ, and a business card for a caterer. The sub-series also supplies various fundraiser forms and an outreach letter asking for support. Documents relating to activities consist of a list of the club’s educational activities, a check request for a spa weekend, tour of the National Cathedral, and information for a tour of Old Town Alexandria. Additionally, there is a Volunteer Service Award and a letter concerning new volunteer involvement opportunities from the Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services. A letter from Robert F. McDonnell, governor of Virginia, dated April 2012 is also included. The letter thanks the club for their support, and gives recognition to the club’s accomplishments.
Series 3: Correspondence, 2007-2011, Box 1
Correspondence includes thank you notes from U.S. soldiers who received care packages from Vale Club. There are five photographs (printed on regular paper from a standard printer) of soldiers. Additionally, there is official Vale Club letterhead and envelopes.
Series 4: Cookbooks, 1986-2001, Boxes 1-2
Cookbooks in this series are primarily from the Gourmet Club (active from 1980 through present), and are published yearly. However, one cookbook included was published by Friends of Vale Schoolhouse. In 2001, Friends of Vale Schoolhouse released a cookbook, Love in Action. Lengthier than Gourmet Club cookbooks, it includes a dedication, table of contents, a history of Vale with memories from club presidents, a plethora of recipes, as well as an index in the back.
Each Gourmet Club cookbook is themed and includes a calendar of dinners, hostess and member information, fees, detailed menus, and explicit responsibilities of members. Most of the cookbooks include a history of the Gourmet Club, and a letter from the chair, but only two include an index. Menus provide the date of the meal, the particular theme, delegation of assignments, and recipes. Two instances of interesting cookbooks are Affairs to Remember (1995-6) and A Second Helping (1994-5). Affairs to Remember is themed after the classic cinematic experience. For example, the menu themed Casablanca features North African cuisine. A Second Helping is musically themed, with the menu focusing on “Back in the U.S.S.R.” based on Russian cuisine.
Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1934-1988, Boxes 5-6
This series contains two scrap books. The first scrapbook is one of two copies (location of second copy unknown).
Scrapbook 1, 1935-1975: A compilation of original documents that represent the early history of the club. It includes records covering Achievement Day reports, fliers for fundraisers, newspaper clippings, and photographs. Some key documents are the first financial report (handwritten) from 1935, a letter to the school board as regarding the purchase of the school, and war activities report from 1943.
Scrapbook 2, 1934-1988: Created in 1988, was made as a supplement to the first scrapbook. About half of the contents are photocopies and not originals and many of the contents are stapled in. The types of records included are photographs, early newsletters, and event schedules. Some of the more interesting records are a 1950s study of the Vale neighborhood that includes maps, and an original letter from the Fairfax County School Board concerning the schoolhouse deed (1965) which contains a brief history of the schoolhouse. The scrapbook also supplies information regarding the new bell tower installed in 1988.
Series 6: Newsletters, 1982-2016, Boxes 3-4
Comprised of monthly Newsletters (September through June). Newsletters include a Letter from the President and general announcements. The newsletters underwent a few name changes in 2001, 2004, and 2006. In 2001, the title of the Newsletters changed to Friends of Vale Schoolhouse Newsletter from Vale Club Newsletters, in 2004 changed to Friends of Vale Schoolhouse, Inc., and in 2006 changed again to Schoolhouse Update.
Series 7: Handbooks, 1985-2009, Boxes 4-5
Released yearly, there are some duplicate handbooks included. Handbooks published earlier in the series include: board members (officers, committee leaders); member names, addresses, phone numbers, and spouse/anniversary info; and a Vale Club Calendar in back. Later handbooks feature additional components: a short article about its “function and purpose;” detailed list of the Executive Board members, and Committee and Activity Chairs; membership responsibilities; member photos; and a list of past club presidents. In the 2001-2002 handbook, the title changed from “Vale Handbook” to “Friends of Vale Schoolhouse Handbook.”
Series 8: Membership Lists, 1984-2000, Box 5
Membership lists are published yearly, with Fall and January update supplements. Some, not all membership lists, include the name of spouse and wedding anniversary, names of children, and years of birth of the children. A list of presidents can be found in the 2001 cookbook in Series 2.
Series 9: Maps, Undated, Oversize Manuscripts Drawer
This series contains two hand drawn maps by George Henry Waple III depicting the Vale community and surrounding area. Vale Club is uncertain as to how these ended up in their possession, and presume Waple completed the maps sometime in the 1980s. Places depicted include Vale, Waples Mill, Fox Mill, and Oakton.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Cooperative Extension Service; Extension Homemakers; Family and Community Education; Friends of Vale Schoolhouse; Jodzies, Florence; Vale Club; Vale Community House; Vale Home Demonstration Club; Vale Schoolhouse; Vale Schoolhouse Associates; Virginia Extension Service; Virginia Polytechnic Institute Farmers Cooperative Demonstration
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Files, 1992-2003
  - Sub-Series 1-1: Extension Club, 1998-1999
    - Fairfax Association for Family and Community Education, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Old Dominion Echoes Newsletters, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Extension Line Newsletters, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sub-Series 1-2: Geographic Boundaries, 2003
    - Geographic boundary files, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sub-Series 1-3: Vale Associates Files, 1999
    - Vale Associates packets, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sub-Series 1-4: Receipts and Finances, 1992-1999
    - Rental agreements and checklist; Insurance value form; various check request forms and receipts., 1992-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Check request forms and receipts, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Social and Activities, 1984-2012
  - Sub-Series 2-1: Boy Scout Proposal, 1997
    - Project proposal and map of project, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sub-Series 2-2: Vale Club Fair, 1984-1999
    - Country Fair and Auction booklets and newspaper clippings, 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Meeting agendas, general planning notes, reports, and fair fliers, 1984-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sub-Series 2-3: Fundraisers, Events, Awards, and Recognitions, 1990-2012
    - Party invitations, directions, auction booklets, menus, DJ lists, check request forms, and tour information., 2000-2010 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - List of education activities, auction booklets, fliers for events, and menus, 1994-2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Auction book, spread sheet of fair sales, poinsettias sale forms, fundraiser check requests and letters, 1996-2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Volunteer Service Award, letter of volunteer recognition, letter from Governor of Virginia, 1990-2012 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series 3: Correspondence, 2007-2011
  - Vale Club letterhead and envelopes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Post cards, thank you notes, and pictures from soldiers, 2007-2011 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Post cards, and thank you notes from soldiers, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series 4: Cookbooks, 1986-2001
  - Cookbook: America the Bountiful, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cookbook: Fantasy Faire, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cookbook: Gay Nineties Gourmet, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cookbook: That's Entertainment, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cookbook: Encore, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cookbook: The Prima Diner, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cookbook: A Second Helping, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cookbook: Affairs to Remember, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cookbook: Whimsical Gatherings, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cookbook: Love in Action, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1934-1988
  - Loose papers from scrapbooks, 1937-1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1935-1975 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1934-1988 (Box 6)
- Series 6: Newsletters, 1982-2016
  - Vale Extension Homemakers Club; Vale Club, 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Vale Club, September through June, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Friends of the Vale Schoolhouse Newsletter, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Friends of the Vale Schoolhouse Newsletter, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Friends of the Vale Schoolhouse Newsletter, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Friends of the Vale Schoolhouse, Inc., 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Friends of the Vale Schoolhouse, Inc., 2005-2006 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Schoolhouse Update, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Schoolhouse Update, 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Schoolhouse Update, 2010-2011 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Schoolhouse Update, 2011-2012 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Schoolhouse Update, 2012-2013 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Schoolhouse Update, 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Schoolhouse Update, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series 7: Handbooks, 1985-2009
  - Vale Club Membership; Vale Club Handbook, 1985-1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Vale Club Handbook, 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Vale Club Handbook, 1998-2001 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Friends of Vale Schoolhouse Handbook, 2001-2004 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Vale Club Handbook; Friends of Vale Schoolhouse, Inc. Handbook, 2004-2009 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Series 8: Membership Lists, 1984-2000
  - Vale Club Membership, 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Vale Club Membership, 1989-1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Vale Club Membership, 1994-2000 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series 9: Maps, Undated
  - Handrawn map of Vale community by George Henry Waple III, Undated (Folder 1)
  - Handrawn map of Vale community by George Henry Waple III (double-sided), Undated (Folder 2)